## DANIEL OTIENO OKWACH

Address: Kongowea, Mombasa, Kenya.

**Phone number:** (+254) 720057533 / 773991561.

**Email:** danielotieno.ke@gmail.com.

## Education

#### 2013-2017: Technical University of Mombasa

Award - Degree (Bachelor of Science in Mathematics and Computer Science).

### 2013-2013: Sponsor an African Scholar (SAAS)

Award – Certificate in computer operations (4 months course)

#### 2009-2012: Mariakani Secondary School

Award – Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education (K.C.S.E)

## **Profile**

An energetic, creative and imaginative Junior Software Developer who is able and dedicated to work alongside other talented IT professionals in creating websites to the very highest standards. I have specialized in both Frontend and Backend Development, experienced with all stages of the development cycle for a dynamic project, well-versed in numerous programming languages including Ruby, Python and JavaScript. I also have interest in Data Science using Python and R. I am open to considering a challenging role with an ambitious company with whom I can commit to and progress within.

# **Achievements and Leadership Positions**

- 2017-present: Organizer of Nairuby Mombasa (Rubyists user group in Mombasa).
- **2016:** Won award for the best personality student of the year.
- 2015 2017: Elected Class Representative (Technical University of Mombasa).
- **2014:** Elected Vice Chairperson (SAAS Youth Group).
- 2011: Won award for the best personality student of the year.
- 2009 2012: Elected Deputy Class president (Mariakani Sec School).

# **Professional Experience**

# Google Africa Developer Scholarship Program

2019 - 2020

# **Program Assistant - Volunteering**

#### **Key activities and responsibilities:**

- Empower talent in Africa through Andela learning community, Google Africa and Pluralsight resources.
- Ensure learners can improve their skills by actively engaging with content on Pluralsight.
- Collaborating with my team to come up with strategies that will help learners to complete the Scholarship.

### **Andela Learning Community**

2018 - 2019

## Learning Facilitator Ambassador - Volunteering

#### **Key activities and responsibilities:**

- Organize and facilitate ALC meetups.
- Make sure more than 50% learner completion of 100% of course contents and projects.
- Make sure more than 75% learner completion of 50-75% of course contents and projects.
- Run 2 meetups between January and February 2019.
- Mentor learners on their online engagement platforms.

<u>Freelance</u> 2017 - 2018

### Key activities and responsibilities:

- Writing cross-browser compliant XHTML, HTML5, CSS3 and JavaScript.
- Develop project concept and maintain optimal workflow.
- Complete detailed programming and development tasks.
- Collaborate with designers to create a clean interfaces.
- Collaborate with other developers through web-based hosting service for version control using git.
- Providing technical support to the end user.

# **Sponsor an African Scholar**

2016 - 2017

#### IT Administrator

### Key activities and responsibilities:

- Maintaining the organization IT network.
- Collecting IT usage statistics.
- Installation of software's.
- Making recommendations for improving the organization website.
- Assisting co-workers with everyday IT needs.

SwahiliBox April 2015- Aug 2015

#### **Web Developer Intern**

Worked as part of a multi-disciplinary team, carrying out ad-hoc tasks as requested by the IT Manager. Had a specific brief to ensure the websites build for customer's precisely matched their requirements.

### Key activities and responsibilities:

- Performed maintenance and updates to existing client Web sites.
- Participated in brainstorming sessions to come up with ideas.
- Documented software and technical specifications.
- Addressed cross-browser compatibility issues.

- Integrated websites with social media platforms.
- Helped end users to solve operating problems.
- Worked on multiple projects simultaneously to a high standard.
- Developing and maintaining the front-end functionality of websites.
- Devising SEO strategies based on specific keywords.
- Participating in discussions with clients to clarify what they want.

### Omollo Onyango Advocates & Company

Aug 2014 - Feb 2015

#### Office Junior

#### **Key activities and responsibilities:**

- Arranging files in the office.
- Helped in troubleshooting office computers.
- Preparing affidavits.
- Configuring office Wi-Fi.
- Storing files in the system.

# **Key Competencies and Skills**

## Web Development

- Knowledge of RUBY, PYTHON, HTML5, CSS3, and JavaScript.
- Strategically thinking through all parts of the design process.
- Integrating new technologies into existing web properties.
- Writing up technical manuals and user instructions.
- Experience of Object-Oriented Programming and Continuous Integration.

#### **Professional**

- Able to organize own workload effectively and prioritize tasks.
- High level of proficiency in Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook).
- Can manage multiple projects in a fast-paced, deadline-driven environment.
- Adaptable and able to quickly pick up new techniques.
- Understanding of W3C standards, web accessibility & best practice.

#### Personal

- Passionate about doing a good job.
- First-rate interpersonal and communication skills, able to easily interact with fellow developers and customers alike.
- Comfortable with being the 'go to' person in a company.
- Always positive, regardless of the challenge ahead.
- Willingness to work with emerging alternative technologies.
- An excellent ability to work both as a team player and as an effective leader.

# **Interest/Activities**

Personal interests are traveling and exploring, photographing, swimming, playing games such as Soccer and touch rugby.

# Referees

## Dr. Aggrey Adem

Director of TUM Enterprise Technical University of Mombasa

Mobile: +254 721261415 Email: aggreyadem@gmail.com

### Mr. Aly Salim Uweso

Deputy Executive Director SwahiliBox Enterprise (M-Power)

Mobile: +254 711763249

Email: alysalim1981@gmail.com

### Ms. Maria Nekesa

Chief Administrative Officer SPONSOR AN AFRICAN SCHOLAR

Mobile: +254 724348945 Email: maria@saas.ie